IU Oral History Archive 1991-1998
Indiana University Libraries
Indiana University Oral History Archive
1991-1998
Indiana University Center for Documentary Research and Practice Indiana University Radio-TV Building, Room 314 1229 E 7th Street Bloomington, IN 47405 Phone: 812/855-2856 Fax: 812/855-0002 E-mail: ohrc@indiana.edu http://mediaschool.indiana.edu/cdrp/oral-history/
Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory
ohrc072
194 interviews. Audiotapes, transcripts, and collateral materials.
This project is a compilation of interviews of subjects with strong ties to and memories of Indiana University, primarily at the Bloomington campus, including former students, faculty, and staff, among others. The information spans most of the twentieth century and deals with the administrations under presidents Herman B Wells, John Ryan, Thomas Ehrlich, and Myles Brand. The project occurred in two parts. The first round of interviews was with administrators, trustees, and other high-ranking members of the university hierarchy. The second round of interviews was with senior faculty from a number of departments in the College of Arts and Sciences. The project is a survey of Indiana University's history as a whole including information about various academic departments, athletics, student organizations, campus growth, and the university's growth in the twentieth century. This project was funded by President Emeritus John Ryan.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains 194 interviews conducted over 7 years. All interviews consist of audio tapes and typed transcripts, as well as collateral materials.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
Oral history interviews conducted by the Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory from 1968 to the present, with particular focus on the history of twentieth-century America and the Midwest.
Interview List
- Adams, William R. "Dick" May 21, 1996, 96-013; 32 pages; 2 tapes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Access Status
  Open
  Scope and Content Note
  Born on February 21, 1923, William R. "Dick" Adams is a native resident of Bloomington, Indiana, who earned his undergraduate degree in zoology from Indiana University in 1944, his masters degree in anthropology in 1949, and joined the faculty of the university in 1955 as a member of the Department of Anthropology. In this interview, he discusses the town of Bloomington, his family's involvement in the stone industry and banking, and his early interaction with Indiana University. In addition, he discusses his various roles as game warden (police officer), anthropologist, zoologist, professor, and banker. Adams speaks of racial problems and crime in Bloomington as they developed in the second half of the twentieth century. Finally, he details the creation of the collection which comprises his bone lab, now under the care of the university.
  Keywords
  Corporation Names
  Bloomington National Bank
  Occupation Names
  anthropologist; anthropology professor; banker; game warden; zoologist
  Personal Names
  Kinsey, Alfred C.; Newman, George; Voegelin, Carl F.
  Place Names
  Bloomington, Indiana
  Subjects
  bone laboratory; local crime; racism
- Anker, Terry March 31, 1994, 91-244; 32 pages; 2 audiotapes, 82 minutes; index; and 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Terry Anker, an Indiana University undergraduate and School of Law alumnus, discusses his memories of and involvement on campus. As a former student body president, Anker recalls his many responsibilities and privileges, the people he met, and the difference he made to Indiana University. In addition, he relates personal anecdotes and memories of student life at the university, his life after college, and of his continuing fondness and predictions for Indiana University. Some topics which received emphasis were Anker's impressions of diversity, campus politics, fraternities and sororities, and of the university presidents, John Ryan and Thomas Ehrlich.
  Indiana University Inter-fraternity Council; Indiana University Office of Risk Management; Indiana University School of Law; United States Student Association
  Baker, John; Boyd, Roselle; Clapacs, Terry; Cross, Pat; Ehrlich, Ellen; Ehrlich, Thomas; Floyd, Ralph; Knight, Bob; Ryan, John W.
  Bloomington, Indiana; Indiana
  apartheid; campus politics; campus safety; diversity; fraternities; graduate study; Herman B Wells Scholars Program; Indiana education; sororities
- Armstrong, William S. May 29, 1991, 91-064; 27 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 95 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  William S. Armstrong served as president of the Indiana University Foundation from 1952 to 1983. He also attended Indiana University as an undergraduate. He discusses Indiana University sports and school spirit during his days as a student. When talking about his time with the Indiana University Foundation, he talks about financial aid, donations, and the development of Crest toothpaste.
  Arthur R. Metz Foundation; Indiana University Department of Chemistry; Little 500; Proctor and Gamble; Purdue University; student foundation
  Family Names
  Getz
  athlete; dairy farmer; Indiana University Foundation president; sports broadcaster
  Biddle, Ward G.; Briscoe, Herman T. "Kay"; Day, Harry; Hope, Bob; Knight, Bob; McGlasen, Tom; Metz, Arthur R.; Muhler, Joseph; Pawner, Nelson; Showalter, Grace M.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Wells, Herman B
  Kentucky
  college sports; Crest toothpaste; financial aid; football; Indiana University Memorial Stadium; research grants; school spirit; Showalter House; student body; women's sports
- Bain, Wilfred C.May 23, 1994, 91-257; 309 pp.;2 tapes 1 7/8 ips, 103 minutes; index;; Freedman, Jean
  Wilfred C. Bain, born January 20, 1908 and died March 7, 1997, discusses his life experiences prior to arriving at Indiana University. He discusses his childhood, family history, and education. He also discusses his experiences teaching at Houghton College and North Texas State University. He discusses changes made to the IU School of Music degree requirements, early music, jazz, and opera. Finally, he discusses his life and activities since retiring from the university in 1978.
  Houghton College; National Association of Schools of Music; New York University; North Texas State University; South Central College; Westminster Choir College; Yale University
  Geographic Names
  Shawville, Quebec; Cattaracus, New York
  Occupations
  minister; professor; teacher
  Appel, Willie; Einstein, Albert; Webb, Charles
  Great Depression; jazz; opera
- Bair, Susanne P. October 25, 1993, 91-213; 14 pages; 1 audiotape, 1 7/8 ips, 42 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Susanne P. Bair, an Indiana University alumnus at the undergraduate, graduate, and doctoral levels, relates her experiences at the university in the late nineteen eighties and early nineteen nineties. The first college graduate in her family, Bair describes the process through which she became interested in and studies athletics, physical education, and athletic administration. As the first female student trustee on the board of trustees, she offers a unique insight into Indiana University controversies over retirement plans, homosexuals in the campus ROTC program, and budget cuts.
  Army ROTC; Athletic Department; School of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation
  athletic director; teacher
  Chamberlain, Phillip; Mobley, Tony; Remley, Mary; Stoner, Richard B.; Wells, Herman B
  budget cuts; homosexuality; Indiana University Kokomo campus; pensions; retirement program
- Banks, Glenn L. October 8, 1993, 91-206; 11 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 23 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Glenn Banks, an Indiana University alumnus from the School of Business' class of 1950, came to the university as a World War II navy veteran. In this interview, Banks recalls his days as a student, but emphasizes the issues that the university was dealing with in the nineteen nineties, including financial and budgetary topics, real estate donations, the campus, and the students. A member of the Indiana University Foundation Board, Banks attributes the success and growth of the university to active and dynamic figures such as Herman B Wells and William Armstrong.
  Indiana University Foundation Board
  Conrad
  Armstrong, William; Wells, Herman B
  Bloomington, Indiana; Mississippi
  campus development; real estate gifts; university funding
- Bannon, William G. March 6, 1992, 91-086; 25 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 93 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1921, William G. Bannon is an Indiana University alumnus from the class of 1943 and a 1945 alumnus of the Indiana University School of Medicine. After brief service in the United States army, Bannon began a successful career as a physician while maintaining an active association with Indiana University. In this interview, he discusses athletics, African-American students at the university, the importance of fraternities and sororities, and the economy of the state of Indiana. In addition, Bannon speaks of the Indiana University board of trustees of which he was a member for several years.
  board of trustees; Indiana University School of Law; Lilly Endowment; Phi Kappa Psi
  physician; teacher
  Bell, Gregory; Campbell, Milt; Crimmins, Bernie; Dumas, Charles; Mays, Willie; Miller, Jean; Wells, Herman B
  African-Americans; diversity; fraternities; Indiana economy; sororities; World War II
- Barnett, John Vincent January 13, 1994, 91-232; 14 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 42 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  John Vincent Barnett was born in Lapel, Indiana, in 1912. He left Indiana University in 1933, but without a degree. He briefly describes student life in the early days of the Great Depression and his career after leaving Indiana University. Further, he describes his activities with the Indiana University Alumni Association, his son's education at the Indiana University School of Law, and challenges for Indiana University leadership in the nineteen nineties.
  Alumni Association; Army ROTC; Indiana Department of Public Welfare; Indiana State Chamber of Commerce; Indiana Vocational Technical College
  Indiana business
  Esarey, Logan; Hennel, Cora; Wells, Herman B
  Lapel, Indiana; Lebanon, Indiana
  Great Depression; Indiana University alumni relations; student life
  A beta videocassette of the interview is housed at the University Archive; a VHS videocassette of the interview is held by President Emeritus John Ryan.
- Bash, James February 24, 1994, 91-238; 16 pages; 1 audiocassette, 43 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  James Bash attended Indiana University School of Law from 1946 to 1949. After graduating, he went to work for Standard Life Insurance Company, remaining there for his entire career. Bash maintained his involvement with Indiana University, serving on the Investment Committee and also acting as President of the Alumni Association from 1982 to 1983. He also discusses his Indiana University School of Law days, what Bloomington was like in the nineteen forties, and changes that have taken place on campus over the past several decades.
  alumni club; Bloomington School of Law; Investment Committee; Standard Life Insurance Company
  alumni association president; attorney
  Wells, Herman B
  campus growth; commencement; English composition; law school; Shawnee Bluffs; student protests; television
- Beering, Steven June 20, 1994, 91-270; 17 pages; 1 audiocassette, 50 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Steven Beering was born in Germany and remained in Europe for the duration of World War II, eventually ending up in a displaced persons camp. He moved to the United States, obtained his medical degree, and became a member of the Indiana University School of Medicine faculty in 1969. From 1973 to 1983, he served as the dean of Indiana University's School of Medicine. He comments on current university problems, like "state-funded" universities and financial problems, and on the state of the nation's health care. He also discusses changes in medicine and medical training.
  IUPUI; Purdue University; United States Air Force
  Air Force physician; assistant dean; medical professor; physician; Purdue University president; School of Medicine dean
  Hinkam, John
  Berlin, Germany; England; Hamburg, Germany
  computers; continuing education; displaced persons camp; health care; hospitals; internationalism; medical costs; medical school; universities; university funding; World War II
- Bepko, Gerald Lewis October 21, 1993, 91-212; 26 pages; 2 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour, 29 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Gerald Bepko, born in 1940, describes his career, which culminated in being named chancellor of Indiana University-Purdue University at Indianapolis (IUPUI). Along the way, he was a law professor, then associate dean, acting, then dean of the law school at IUPUI. Bepko describes the challenges of an urban university like IUPUI. Bepko also describes his own education and early career as an FBI agent.
  Chicago-Kent Law School; FBI; IUPUI; IUPUI School of Law; IUPUI University Library; Purdue University; United States Department of Justice
  FBI agent; law professor; law school administrator
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Meredith, James; Read, Tom
  Chicago, Illinois; Indianapolis, Indiana; Mississippi; Oxford, England
  1965 Voting Rights Act; African-Americans; health care costs; race relations; university funding; voting rights marches
- Black, Joseph M. May 8, 1992, 91-102; 15 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 40 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on September 17, 1918, Joseph M. Black is an Indiana University alumnus from the class of 1941 and a 1944 alumnus of the Indiana University School of Medicine. After serving two years in the United States army, Black began a successful career as a physician. In the early nineteen sixties, he was president of the alumni association and has served for over twenty years on the Indiana University board of trustees. Black discusses his relations with Herman B Wells and other Indiana University presidents. In addition, he recalls memories of his days as a student at the university including the days of World War II, the growth of the university, and fraternity life.
  board of trustees; Indiana University Alumni Association; Indiana University School of Medicine
  physician
  Barker, Clare Wright; Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B
  fraternities; regional medical program; university growth; World War II
- Bluemle, Robert May 23, 1994, 91-260; 9 pages; 1 tape, 30 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Born on November 6, 1933, Robert Bluemle received his undergraduate degree from Indiana University in 1956 and later earned his MBA from the School of Business. Bluemle then pursued a successful career in law. In this interview, he recalls his days as a student at the university, including his time as student body president. He also speaks of memories of how McCarthyism and its adversaries were active on campus. Throughout the interview, Bluemle emphasizes the wonderful contributions Herman B Wells made to Indiana University and the greatness of Wells' character.
  Green Feathers; Indiana University School of Business
  Georges, Robert A.; Wells, Herman B
  McCarthyism
- Boaz, Estella May 10, 1996 May 31, 1996 June 07, 1996, 96-014; 29 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 120 minutes; index;; Kraemer, Peter
  Estella Boaz was a student from 1917 to 1923 and she majored in Spanish with a minor in English. After graduating she taught Spanish in Clayton, New Mexico from 1924-1926. She discusses her childhood and family growing up in Crawfordsville, Indiana. She discusses her time as a student at Indiana University, specifically mentioning football games and classes she attended. She also discusses the impact of World War 1 on campus and her family.
  Red Cross
  Clayton, New Mexico; Crawfordsville, Indiana; Newman, Illinois
  professor; teacher
  Bryan, William Lowe; Hill, John; Knight, Bob; Lead, Roy
  farms; football; language instruction; tutoring
- Bogle, Victor M. August 20, 1991, 91-074; 22 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 69 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Victor Bogle was an administrator, professor, and director of the Kokomo Extension Center or regional campus, as it came to be known. Bogle discusses Indiana University Kokomo's evolution through the years and the changes it manifested under the administrations of different Indiana University presidents, including Herman B Wells, Elvis J. Stahr, and John Ryan. In addition, he speaks of the relationship between the Kokomo campus and that of Indiana University in Bloomington. The interview also includes information about bureaucracy and campus agitation with regard to Indiana University Kokomo.
  Indiana University Kokomo
  history professor; university chancellor
  Hunt, Virgil; Miller, Herbert; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Wells, Herman B
  campus protests; Indiana University regional campuses; university bureaucracy
- Bolinger, Donald J., II October 13, 1993, 91-209; 18 pages; 1 audiocassette, 47 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Donald Bolinger is a second generation Indiana University grad. After receiving his BA, he also received his law degree from Indiana University in 1982. Always interested in politics, Bolinger served as the student body president during his third year of law school. He discusses his time as an undergraduate and law student, focusing on his professors and the experiences of himself and his friends. After law school, Bolinger returned to Kokomo to practice law. He also teaches at Indiana University's Kokomo campus.
  Indiana University; Indiana University Kokomo
  attorney; dorm president; law professor; student body president
  Edlin, George; Gambill, Chris; Gros Louis, Kenneth R.R.; Gross, Robert; Jordan, Dean
  Kokomo, Indiana
  alcohol; book co-op; campus radicalism; commercialism; law school; parking; recession; Socratic method; student government
- Borkenstein, Robert F. August 22, 1996, 96-021; 30 pages; 2 tapes; index; article; Kraemer, Peter
  Born on August 31, 1912, Robert F. Borkenstein was a member of the Indiana University until 1983 and chair of what is now the Department of Criminal Justice until 1970. He was one of the founders of the study of this area at Indiana University. Beginning with a fledgling department entitled Police Administration, he speaks of the development of the criminal justice field, alternately called criminology, which included aspects of the forensic sciences, law enforcement, sociology, psychology, and law. Borkenstein recalls many of the important changes the field has undergone including the development of breathalizer testing, blood alcohol testing, the Miranda decision, and, more recently, DNA evidence. Some of the most prominent institutions in this interview are the Indiana State Police, the Indiana State Police Academy, Northwestern University, Indiana University, and the Federal Bureau of Investigation.
  Center for Studies of Law in Action; FBI; Indiana State Police; Indiana State Police Academy; Indiana University Department of Criminal Justice; Indiana University Department of Police Administration; Northwestern University
  criminal justice professor
  blood alcohol tests; forensic sciences; international law enforcement; law enforcement; Miranda rights; police training
- Braden, Samuel May 6, 1991, 91-065; 20 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 67 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Samuel Braden received his Ph.D. from Indiana University in economics and remained with the university for over forty years. He was a professor and administrator at Indiana University Bloomington from 1937 to 1967 and then moved on in the same capacity to Indiana University Southeast. He also talks about the state university system, the growth of Indiana University regional campuses, and the changes that have taken place at Indiana University over the last thirty years.
  Indiana Conference of Higher Education; Indiana University Credit Union; Indiana University Division of Undergraduate Development; Stillman College
  economics professor; economist; Latin Affairs Committee chairperson; missionary; Seminary board member; undergraduate development dean; undergraduate development vice president; university administrator
  Gray, Don; Gucker, Frank G.; Wells, Herman B
  Evansville, Indiana
  campus growth; geography; Indiana education; Indiana University regional campuses; internationalism; provincialism; reading lists; residence hall libraries; World War II
- Brooks, John W. June 6, 1996, 96-015; 38 pages; 2 tapes; index; newsletter and speech; Kraemer, Peter
  Born on October 24, 1943, John W. Brooks came to Indiana University in 1962 on a track scholarship and stayed to earn his undergraduate, masters, and doctoral degrees. Brooks then began his career working the Department of Financial Aid at Indiana University and progressed through various positions to his current job as the Director of Corporate and Foundation Relations at the university. Brooks speaks of his many experiences at Indiana University as an African-American including those involving racism, segregation, integration, interracial dating, and the Civil Rights Movement. In addition, Brooks speaks of his involvement in the fraternity, Omega Psi Chi, and the environment of the community of Bloomington, Indiana. He also discusses the minority students at Indiana University, the Groups program, and the development of plans for the Neal Marshall Black Culture Center. He cites Herman Hudson and Jimmy Ross as two colleagues who exerted much positive influence at the university.
  Neal Marshall Cultural Center; Omega Psi Chi
  Hudson, Herman; Ross, Jimmy
  Civil Rights Movement; diversity; fraternities; Groups program; integration; interracial dating; local crime; minority students; race relations; segregation; student housing
- Burton, Robert E. September 5, 1991, 91-076; 15 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 56 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Robert Burton came to Indiana University during World War II to be the Assistant Cashier and Ticket Manager. He quickly took on the job of Assistant to the Controller and stayed in this position until his retirement in 1989. He discusses how Indiana University has changed over the years, the different presidents, changes in the student body, influential personalities, and memorable events.
  American Legion; board of trustees; Indiana University Business Office; Treasurer's Office
  assistant cashier; assistant secretary to board of trustees; assistant to the chief business officer; assistant to the comptroller; board of trustees secretary; teacher; ticket manager; United Way board member
  Biddle, Ward G.; Deiss, Charles Frederick; Ehrlich, Thomas; Fisher, L.L.; Franklin, Joe; Kinsey, Alfred C.; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B
  African-Americans; campus growth; segregation; student organizations; trailers; trucks; World War II
- Byrd, Cecil May 16, 1994, 91-255; 16 pages; 1 audiocassette, 35 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Cecil Byrd obtained his masters and doctoral degrees from Indiana University in the late nineteen thirties, and early nineteen forties. He remained at the university as a curator, eventually becoming the university librarian. He discusses his memorable professors and classes, the growth and changes at the libraries, the changes in the university over time, and the highlights of his career.
  Indiana University Lilly Library; United States Navy
  assistant director of libraries; associate director of libraries; librarian; rare books curator; special collections curator; university librarian
  Buley, Roscoe Carlyle; Lynch, William Orlando; Wells, Herman B
  computers; curriculum; Indiana University regional campuses; libraries; library collections; World War II